welcome everyone to voices whisper makey
I'm joined once again by my good friend
and I don't know Mike oh wait error on
this path that we're all treading during
the meeting crisis and the meta crisis
and many of you have already seen him in
a couple of previous Wizards with the
baby and his eloquence and his insight
his dexterity of mind and his quick and
wonderful good humor
I've always welcomed envoys of a welcome
name in Moscow hi John that's a lovely
introduction thank you here's where I
thought we could start because what's
been on my mind this morning is kind of
the interface between subjective and
objective in terms of contemplating
beauty what's the role of projection in
there because when we make a mental
image of the philosopher or practitioner
contemplating the beautiful and all of
the positive effects that might have on
a person we tend to think of the
contemplate ER and the beautiful right
but a lot of its got to be like a jet
fighter pilot that the targeting
indicators are on the screen of his
Medic so I agree is the beauty something
that we're sending around and putting on
top of the perceptual target and to what
degree is it's better or even more
practical to think of it as being out
there mmm okay that's really really good
question I don't know if you've seen any
logos I had with their new Sweeney Oh
before I forget you and Chris have to
talk at some point that would be I think
a wonderful conversation yeah well Chris
that but we just haven't got it set up
yet okay and so because it's I it's more
and more at the core of the whole deal
logos dialectic project because there's
something about the unification of logos
and and the
and the beautification of a way of life
there in that is central to dialectical
practice and so yeah this has been a
really important concern for me so I
wanna I wanna I want to maybe let's take
a couple steps initial steps and
thinking about this question and the
move to people that have recently had a
huge influence on my thinking about
beauty are Ellen's Gary's book beauty
and Wyatt prepares us for truth and
justice and and then the work by Han his
book saving Beauty let's start with mine
because that to me that was really
interesting because it resonated with
his work on time and his work on arrows
also being for tronic themes that really
really really really talking to so he
talked about he talked about the how and
we why do you think let's put it this
why do we need to save you he thinks
beauty is being Ross which already means
he's thinking he's thinking there's
something objective to beauty right
there he thinks the beauty of being lost
because we are reducing it when he calls
the aesthetics of the smooth that we
we're assimilating beauty to what is you
know what is smooth and he talks about
all these works of art now I think he
gets a little bit too extreme but that's
that's he's wantin his style because I
do think there's an element of genuine
aesthetics to smooth things when I'm
doing the form I want the form to be
smooth that's okay but I take his point
to be this what he dislikes about the
aesthetics of the smooth is it removes
what he seems to what he argues is a
central feature of beauty which points
directly to your question which and
that's it the central feature of beauty
that he is pointing to is degree to
which it transcend our capacity for
assimilation the degree to which we are
struck by beauty as we used to say a
while ago
and he brings out that connects up with
his idea that genuine arrows is right is
to confront something other than oneself
to be drawn to and if you're only if
you're only doing a roast in an
assimilation fashion you've reduced
Airrosti consumption and you know Plato
talks about the correct response to
beauty is generative not consumptive you
want to as twit Plato says you want to
in the symposium you want to generate
beautiful things in beauty like the
response to beauty is you want to it's
any he directly you know analogizes it
to sexual reproduction you want to
reproduce beauty you want to gyp you
want to be this generative thing you
want I am pregnant by it you want to
conceive and give birth to it and so I
think that that's one thing I want to
throw out there that that there that we
might be able to look not in the content
of beauty for the objective but degree
to which we are struck by what we cannot
assimilate and that therefore beauty
would be on a continuum with Wonder and
awe but also before and when and we
might want to explore the strange family
relationship between horror and beauty
and why there's an aesthetic of work for
people that's which has always been
deeply perplexing to me sort of
philosophically so that's one and then
this I find very convergent also
platonically with Ellen scary argument
that what pewdie does for us if you'll
allow me I'll use a little bit of the
language I've been trying to coined a
phenomenological language but I think
this is very consonant with Sochi that's
about when you see if you see a
beautiful cheese and your example right
and you're struck by it first of all she
has what on is talk to you but you're
struck by it and then she points out two
things which are really interesting
there's what I would call there's an
experience of the morning
that's the part I didn't know please
could be like this right there's the ah
right so there's the mortise and then
but there's also there's the unique
unrepeatable 'ti about this three like
you get how it's it's it's unlike all
the other bits right it will show you
what any tree could be but it's also
unlike any tree you've seen before it
has its own particular specialist it's
non categorical unique presencing and so
right and she she argues that beauty
therefore is training and she needs if i
think it's a deep sense like the dojo
askesis spiritual practices is training
for truth because if we can't if we
don't have a capacity to be struck by
what is more right there the mystery of
participation and also yeah you know
that sensibility transcendence speaking
up on what is unique and unrepeatable
here now right which is this would be I
would argue disappear and then from
ESA's parts of wisdom right she argues
that we can't genuinely preserve pursue
either truth as an epistemic value or
justice as a social value because she
seems truth as that which is trying to
take us in for the more but also bring
it into what is contextually most
relevant now and I think that's very
important and she's just this is always
trying to there's much more to humanity
but there's also something special and
unique about this person right here
right now so she argues that beauty
prepares us for truth adjusted so what
I'm arguing for I guess I guess I make
the argument is that I think there is
something I don't know it's quite a
object it but at least ran detective
because I think she's arguing that
beauty the degree to which we pick up on
what Han talked about about its Cressida
striker
Beauty is an affordance a nasties that
the training affordance for truth and
justice so that's my line
that's how I'm thinking of you need a
lot these days so there's a lot to give
you but I know you'll do a lot with it
sure I mean I agree very much with the
sort of the need to think beauty is
having an excessive dimension yeah both
in its positive in its negative sense I
think the idea of dark beauty is an
interesting one and the beauty or pick
up on and it also reminds me of just the
uncanny beautiful in general yeah what's
that quote from Andre Breton and the
surrealist that I think Breton
said quoting someone else that Beauty
had to be like the chance meeting of a
sewing machine and an umbrella on a
dissecting table uncanny juxtaposition
to give it the vividness they're looking
for to get the sense of hyper conscious
beauty yeah so that element of excess
vividness with it I think is important
and I think we've traditionally used the
idea that it's out there beyond us too
as a way of conceptualizing that
mourneth yes but I think we can probably
get that more nests by looking at the
way our parts come together to create
something that's greater than our
current homeostatic self experience sure
right like if I let's imagine I have all
these subjective intelligence systems
that make me up and if enough of them
were to come together and be reflected
back to me it would be more than my
current self awareness and self image
doesn't mean I didn't produce it from
the inside there put it on the screen
now we could still imagine that it's out
there may have extreme heuristic value
to imagine that it's beyond us and there
may be I think a number of things in the
you know ontology of the computations
that make up reality that predispose
certain things to being easier to
project beauty upon but I I don't think
that we lose the more nests and the
sacred other nests
that we get from Beauty by imagining
that a lot of the mechanism is
generative from within us by creating a
more than the sum of the parts
effect of the systems that we have okay
so I like that it sounds neat and if
this is wrong interject that you're
proposing no dynamical complexification
that produces an emergent function so
then I respond to that would be again
that sounds transactive rather than
subjective to me because a function only
exists in so far as it can function
right so it has to couple to the
environment in some way right and
because if it doesn't couple to the
environment it may not function or in
fact I don't know what what it would
mean to say that it's a function so let
me let me make sure that I'm
understanding you you don't want to sit
like so I've been playing with this term
a lot Kerri has invested in the B but he
calls the inventio of the inner self
because the Latin word means both
discovery and adventure which which
relief works
the dichotomy we're addressing here
right now so I tend to think and that's
come up in the discussion of beauty as
an event here right that it's both in
the sense it's something that our
psyches are inventing but then that
invention genuine discloses something
real about the world to us it's also
discovery that's what I get in inspiring
that there must be something we like
there must be something in the
functioning that is disclosing something
now about the world such that it makes
the training for truth and justice a
real training a real functionality
that's what I said yeah I would assume
that like if we imagine a situation in
which the majority of this effect is
produced from in US but it's produced in
relationship to the actual patterns of
the actual universe some of which make
that more available to us than others
that we've developed this capacity
because it's a very general capacity
right it's one way of saying that is
that it trains us for the other values
yeah yeah no we can say it's among the
other value
we could say it's at the heart of
cognition itself because like in some of
the eastern trainings just to perceive
anything has an element of perfection to
it yes so it's an extremely general
capacity that we've evolved and if we've
evolved that we've evolved it in an
adaptive fashion to environments so that
it's one thing to think about what our
role is in creating the effect the
aesthetic effect through a coordination
of stimulations that feedback to us but
that process is embedded within a
relationship to the rest of the
universe's patterns as well and we've
been predisposed to it over billions of
years of training to be able to take
advantage of that mechanism because it's
adaptive an ongoing fashion so that I
think that's yeah I think that's right I
think that some more speculatively now
we're already being speculative but even
more so you know I think beauty is the
way in which we train relevance
realization better holding in on what is
just or what is good or what is true
it's I think it's how we get it more
normatively oriented at frame and so I
think it has I think it's exactly doubt
of our capacity for all the you know the
sensory motor and cognitive optimal
gripping that we're always doing it's
why me generally will talk about dogs as
opposed to cocker spaniels or mammals
right because that's sort of an optimal
grip for interacting with those animals
given our general context it's not
enough differences we've got enough of
the relevant differences enough of the
relevant similarities right and and so I
think of beauty as a realization very
much like insight that's why we're
struck by beauty I think of it as a
restructuring and realization of
precognition of optimal gripping so that
it's oh wait I'm optimally gripping
better than I was before the world and
so when so when I'm thinking about it
more in cognitive sciences that's not
like that's how I see it
and that's of course it's going to be
tremendously adaptive and valuable to us
does that resonate with what you're
saying it does and it leads me to a kind
of question about what is the utility or
significance of practices that lead
people to have a very diverse experience
of optimal gripping in a basic sense and
what I mean by that is suppose I
underwent a quasi Buddhist training
which allowed me to get better and
better at seeing the beauty in any
perceptual moment in any act of
cognition I'm observing and reflecting
upon the fact that any cognitive moment
is successful I'm accomplishing optimal
gripping just by seeing something yeah
so now am i I've made it super normative
my experience of optimal gripping
because I'm doing it on everything
that's coming up is this a superior
state in which I'm super adapted to be
able to perform this function or have I
settled for the least possible value
have I become hooked on the most basic
form and I've gone into a cul-de-sac
well it doesn't it seems to me that
that's a bifurcation point in
development because I could see and
because the Buddha definitely warns
about the second he warns you know the
sort of the contentedness
something like the contentedness of the
cabbage right it's not a sense of oh no
so but I think other traditions have
recognized the possibility but so but
there's also the opposite affordances
there because I can see the capacity for
deep learning I can see by running like
really intensifying all the variations
of the optimal gripping diversify that
differentiated right that by
differentiating it in this and this is
not a contradiction in a very integrated
practice could afford the opposite where
I get you know a very comprehensive
install and I grasp
deeper invariant principles that
generalize much more powerfully this is
what you do in deep learning right you
run the variations and they give you the
compression and you read the variation
right then I can see that affording a
deep learning that again we colonizes
does a that provides like just an
insight about this flower or this cable
but an insight into being by the
systemic incited to be optimal optimal
grip and why I think that's relevant is
because I've argued in the series that I
think one of the features of these hires
needs of consciousness our people are
getting into a kind of flow state with
this sort of meta optimal gripping but
optimal grip on this and this much
optimal grip in per se you're sort of
that's what because they get this
intense and if this is where this is AG
and we're sorry comes in the beauty
leads into it an intense sense of
realness at the same time and and so for
me the way I've tried to understand that
is okay you can't understand it in terms
of the content they produce the
propositions because they're all over
the place and they contradict each other
so I think that where that normative
judgment of the beautiful realness is
coming from is something like you know
enhanced meta optimal grip so I think
that what you propose could be training
that affords that kind of Satori but it
could also be abused
why not everything can be abused that
could be abused for a kind of like you
said a called the sack a kind of like
just the general contentedness with the
obvious Ness of everyday experience
which is sometimes I think mistaken for
an interpretation of them well you were
saying that I thought about because
outside of the cul de sac interpretation
there is this sense that a a higher more
abstracted more generalized version of
what the optimal grip move is is
experienced by people who practice that
as being a superior level of development
yep right so then put me in mind of
you know pre and trans and superior and
enter your modes of development because
one of the things you could say about
people who undertake risky or
self-destructive behavior is that they
might be seeking a dark beauty effect
because they aren't succeeding at
getting a higher optimal grip on the
Gnostic you died down into the reflected
image of the depths right because you
mistaking it for the the the light from
above sure have you seen there's movie
300 then there's a sequel to it about
the Athenians versus the Persians
yeah the Athenians go to the Spartans
and try to enlist their aid
the Spartans turn them down and the
general goes back to his men and they
say you know are the Spartans with us he
says no the Persians offered them
something they couldn't refuse
what's that he says a beautiful death so
they're gonna a regressive Beauty was
the best thing they could hope for
presumably because they weren't
confident in their ability to access a
more complicated beauty yeah again I
think you're speaking towards something
that I've seen discuss mentioned in
multiple wisdom traditions
so obviously the gnostic tradition very
talked about that i just reference that
that platonist talked about it because
of a riff on narcissus and his version
of that is persistence falls in love
with the reflection rather of beauty and
then falls to ISM into the water and
drowns right and so yeah I think that's
a very real possibility so that's I'm
sort of two things and they feel like
they want to come together because your
your your have your heads up display
metaphor keeps coming back because I've
also got this third idea of and I think
it connects to this I don't know how I'm
asking for your help right I think it's
when we connect them it will also be an
answer or to the question you posed or
the problem you posed so let's
my information bears out because I'm
also thinking of beauty as right and
this because you know we talked about
the often it's associated with more
realness right like what's called what's
nowadays both amplified reality you know
and when you when you actually projected
image or project a virtual image on to
the real image in order to actually
disclose things that are otherwise
visible you know you do this immediately
but you also do it in real science so
the scientists you think the Rovers on
Mars
you know the completely of
verisimilitude images that veridical
images are kind of useless they when
they do is they mark them all off and
they color them and they put lines on
them and they do all this stuff to
manipulate their salience and then what
happens is they go five they get a
pop-out experience ago all right this
and then they get the topography right
and so that's what I mean by an ant so
there's a sensor which is projection
because they're they're doing what you
said they're getting all their faculty
they're sort of triggering their own
cognition but what it does is in fact it
actually does blow there's something
that was otherwise invisible to them and
that's of course what a heads-up display
is doing to right for the pilot because
it's projecting everything on to the
windshield but it's allowing them to
track and see things that they're
unaided vision can't trap is that okay
if I misappropriated your metaphor so
far so good okay so is it possible that
what we are being taught that the
metaphors the myth you know you know I
mean use that term positively not
pejoratively right is that people are
treating the images okay clean right
yeah right
they're looking at them rather than
looking through them and that's how they
make the fundamental miss taken right
you see what I'm trying to suggest to
you that I used to use to use mauryans
term they they treat it as an idle
rather than an icon and that picks up
certainly on narcissus because that's
what the finest seems to be indicating
so there's my first attempt at an answer
yeah that's interesting and I
it's a good approach because when we try
to think the pattern of the encounter
with the beautiful the positive version
of that is so close to the negative
version of yes that's I mean the idea of
a window with a pattern on it right and
so it's the same window on the same
pattern but you either see through it or
just see it I mean if you were to look
at it rather than through it then you
are kind of trapped in a smaller loop of
cognition yes revolve around the
attractor state of a lower level of
beautiful cognition rather than allowing
you out into a higher level right
reciprocal narrow way rather than a
reciprocal opening and it would tend
through that you know comport you
towards more addictive ways of being and
seeing and cognition rather than you
know growth and transcendent
transcending forms of seeing and being
so that seems to me like you know it's
like I feel like we're up to you as far
as soon like we're beautifying our
speech so that we're on the track of the
truth that's what that's what it feels
like to me yeah it's uh it seems like
it's a more demanding function to get
that transparency that opaqueness
because it's a bit like stereoscopic
vision right yeah two things at the same
time which is a more cognitively
demanding task and therefore more likely
to fail for a lot of people that's about
that but the demand so it's almost
there's going to be there's going to be
a lot of cognitive inertia because of
the cognitive miser
that is going to resist that and
presumably there has to be something I
think you liked about something like
this before there has to be something
like a certain degree of arousal as
activation energy that will afford the
complexification to start taking place
because there's not a vision is a kind
of cognitive complexity patient
they're stopping vision is actually an
even better thing for what applies
because you notice how it brings
together your earlier idea because
you're actually complexified to inner
thing
right but it actually discloses
something about reality that needs to be
disclosed which is the dimension of
depth I think that's very very good
so it's something like the image we want
is right somehow would integrate
stereoscopic vision and then looking
through the painted window rather than
just looking at the painted window or
something like that we combine those
together yeah for me partly because I'm
first in a lot of these theories about
levels of layers of developmental
complexity that I start thinking about
each more comprehensive and folding
level as needing to synchronize the
functions of a lot of different pieces
yes
seeing a thing and seeing through a
thing those are two functions that have
to be really well synchronized and a
host of other ones right arousal in
terms of energy production which means
your lifestyle and your physiology all
these things have to be on board to
sustain that higher level and if it
starts to break down it breaks down in
the form of those functions some of them
coming offline or maybe they stop
synchronizing which leads me to think
sociologically because you know one of
the things if you just stand back and
look at the you know trash fire that
appears to be the United States lately
one of the things you see there arguably
is the functions of modernity not
synchronizing you see right the modern
police force running up against the
freedom of the individual you see
corporate freedoms running up against
freedoms of the press you see all these
different functions interfering with
each other rather than synchronizing or
or also synchronizing and like we talked
about the sort of parasitic processing
where because everything has side
effects try other than the intended
effects and so a lot of the side effects
I think we're also starting to reinforce
each other in negative patterns if an
orchestra started to fail right you
still might get the drummer and the
flautist circling each other so I wonder
if this leads back to the aesthetics of
poor
I'm wondering if part of the attraction
I think that's the right word what are
the attraction to the aesthetics of
horror is because I mean it split poor
puts you into a high level of arousal
for sure and horror also is really it's
really it really challenges your sense
that you actually have an optimal grip
it has a real potential to threaten you
out of just looking at and say no no
you're not seeing you're not seeing it
until you bet he's challenging you to
like that's why it's pretty close to aw
because I is like you're all I am not
seeing it but I might actually see it
like we're Horrors I'm not seeing if I'm
not gonna see it and that's really great
but I'm sorry that other than suggestion
that may be part of why because it would
help to alleviate the paradox because
the content of horror should be deeply
aversive to us right stuff is
threatening us right
but maybe part of the attraction and
that right is when we get a sense like I
said of a combination of two things that
could potentially be beneficial if they
were appropriately coordinated which is
a high level of arousal and a deep sense
that we haven't got a appropriate grip
on things and we need to see more deeply
than we're currently seeing that's a
suggestion yeah there's an element there
of somebody who's lost and wants to go
back to the crossroads right go back to
the bifurcation points because then the
bifurcation point could go either way
it's like what's the attraction to
standing at the edge of a cliff that's
really hot right some people it's going
to give them a little extra thrill and
remind them that they want to live and
for other people it's risky because the
idea that you might throw yourself off
is gaining ground in your mind exactly
so I wondered so I wonder then if I
wonder if ah is more
where's that sweet point I mean I'm in
discussion with Brian Houston man we're
running must opponent was running funny
like he's running experiments I put it
on off and also with Jennifer stellar
and Jensen camp and Michele Ferrari
we're running experiments on aw and it
is interesting what seems to do in
contrast to just the just experiences of
beauty because odd generally has a huge
impact on meaning in life so people feel
really connected to something that's
real that's that realness that they
don't necessarily have with these our
cultural understanding the movie so that
contrast is clearly coming out they
don't get an enhanced sense of purpose
so it's not telling at all all right so
contrary to meaning they're just having
the purpose no it's not Offshore's it's
not no no no no what's really
interesting it goes towards what we're
talking about here is you get you get an
appreciable increase in people's ability
to pick up on patterns deeper more
complex patterns that they couldn't pick
up off the floor there might be a way in
which the meaningfulness of odd does
have a tell it component okay that it
makes you super aware of your capacity
to produce that experience from out of
your own machinery case you're reminded
of that's the purpose of life and it is
possible for me to do this I can see
that I can see that I think it's
interesting that the way you did that
because that reminds me again of what we
were talking about I mentioned both
Plato that what happens is you get a
generative response that's what you just
did your responses oh I want to generate
I want to generate right I want to be
able to generate more and more of this
and there's a sense in which you're also
a form a reality for lack of a better
word the world to be more generative in
what it could disclose to people in
terms of its potential for
intelligibility so I agree with that I
think that's right and I don't know
that's pilot or that tarantella I don't
know if you're stating a purpose
as opposed to an ideal it sounds more I
burnt young to be an adjective all but
that could be equivalent
it's a different kind of a purpose it's
an herb purpose or a mat a purpose of
some kind because it doesn't super
meaningful experience and odd doesn't
necessarily come along with or doesn't
have to come along with some kind of
cognitive content about what the purpose
might be yeah if we think of self-aware
content about purposes as secondary to
what purpose really is then we could
argue that it's a purpose right like no
if most purposes are animating rather
than self-aware yeah that's fine so why
that won't show up on the standard
measures because the standard measuring
the purpose understand purpose as a
future state of affair so a purpose is
kind of a is your most important goal
that you're working towards and so
you're not working towards a particular
future state of affairs of what you're
talking about here you're working more
for an on an ongoing constraint or
virtue for your for your all of your
existence you're working for a
qualitative subset of affairs to be
privileged in your future outcomes yes
between goals and ideals along just that
line for an ideal is like the idea of
honesty is just like you said you know
in many different possible future States
I want to act in this manner as opposed
to I want to be wealthy which is there's
a future state that I want to be
definitively arrived at that's
interesting in terms of what we were
previously discussing about the
possibility of expansive or regressive
winners of this phenomenon because you
might say I've got a lot of things going
on I've got a lot of purposes not just
one but a bunch and at some point there
they converge at a principle a virtue of
some kind that I'm working towards
however they might also converge to a
lower set of those virtues right so the
person who is moving through their
behavior towards a self-destruct
outcome but it's also moving towards a
beautiful darkness towards something
they're gonna say this is reality man
you know so there's a lot of virtues
although they're in a more compressed
form that's that's cool okay so that
room this is what came up for me with
that so I talked about the problem
aspect is five the therapeutic work and
you'll see why that's relevant to what
you said in just a second so somebody
comes in and well what's wrong
you know I'm too stubborn I just I got
everybody's coming on so confrontational
and stubborn and no I got it I gotta let
go oh that's interesting and then you
talk to them for a while and you get
them off and you get them into sort of
the monologue autobiography they can
just you a lot of human beings pretty
naturally once you get past a few
moments or you know politeness right and
then while they're doing that you ask
tell me something about yourself that
you really like and let's say well I
persevere I really keep going no matter
what and you said and so so right and
then part of the therapy is to get them
to see the non-logical identity the
aspects of identity lie between
stubbornness and perseverance right and
that's a very difficult thing to do so
here's a question because it seems to me
like that aspect shift is is somehow
aligned with what we were talking about
earlier the ability to see through
rather than look at like the person who
like the person because it's like it
strikes me like the stereoscopic vision
right because the person in therapy
needs to get a stereoscopic vision on
stubbornness and perseverance in order
to break through to the depths whereas
the person who's trapped is only looking
at the stubbornness and looking at the
perseverance that does that make yeah
absolutely like if I imagine a kind of
cartoonish image where we all come built
in with these instincts and some of
those instincts are virtue experiences
yeah
and these
can develop analogous to say Howard
Gardner's intelligences something like
that right the developmental phases of
these virtues would involve a
complexification which has to involve a
splitting and a synchronizing so you've
got you know I really am pursuing a
virtue here I'm persevering and you need
to then help that person grow to the
next more complex stable stage of that
virtue which involves teasing it apart
from its reciprocal but holding them in
a synchronized way a stereoscopic
fashion so that you can operate at the
next attractor level or whatever we want
to call that so this action sounds a lot
like it's what you just said was
beautiful by the way that really yes
that's great
and now what it sounds equally analogous
to is a dynamic interpretation of
Aristotle's golden mean right that what
you're always trying to do by a and you
know courage is in between calories and
through hardiness like and here so
you're sort of doing almost a two-way
stereoscopically right and you're doing
all of this complexification and virtual
engineering so that now I'm going to do
a move here came up in the discussion
first of all I want to flag something
just as a general note what's happening
here is interesting because for me the
process and you know I'm gonna go mana
just for a second and then I'll return
all right we're doing something we're
doing a kind of argumentation in which
instead of propositions were making
proposals and then what we're doing is
the proposals are doing this gathering
right right so it's it's normal it's not
the logical progression of premises
although we're not we're not I hope
we're not violating logical coherence
but there's something much more it's
much more that sense of the logos we're
fine we're gathering things together and
see so that they come to belong together
and then afford another proposal that
gathers things together and this is what
I think is flipping that I want to
Portmore I'm trying to
located apart before a grounded and say
we need to be paying attention to this
kind of argumentation as opposed to the
strict logical progression of premises
this though there's no ghost progression
of proposals strikes me as much more
important for what we need to do when we
are trying to cultivate wisdom or virtue
so I just wanted to put that out there
as something to flag and Expo K because
you're helping me develop and explicate
and understand what this is you know I
have a lot of training in formal
argumentation and I'm not I'm not saying
should just you know get rid of that get
into really nearly romanticism or
something but there's something more
going on here and I have a sense that
you're feeling and experiencing it too
and I just wanted to note that for
people because I think noting the
process is relevant on to what we're
actually talking about because we're
actually trying to beautify the
discourse of the communication so that
being said within that context that that
framing of argumentation I made an
argument with too because it's a series
of proposals I made an argument to Chris
and Andrew that there seems to be
therefore a deep connection between
virtue beauty and wisdom given what
we've just said right about this
complexification and and then going back
to the seeing through right and also
this is meta optimal gripping and I
proposed to them that wisdom also has
because I want to I want to turn the
stereoscopic vision sort of this way to
link it into the reciprocal opening so
this is what I'm proposing there's a
kind of stereoscopic vision that's
proposed in wisdom in aerosol namely
like there's Sophia which is out into
the morning and then there's furnaces
which is into the sentence I think
that's Barry as clearly I think that's
all those terms be and so there's a
stereoscopic vision to wisdom if I can
put it that way and then I'll throw in a
Socratic idea
and the Socratic idea is that virtues
are always just specific enactment
enactments of wisdom that being
courageous is how I'm wise in this
situation and being kind is high and
wise in this situation that you've got
to give me the stereoscopic sensitive
wisdom for that to really be I think a
viable proposal and then I could if you
give me that and you give what you said
about beauty here's a proposal that I
think is a very important proposal that
virtue is the beauty of wisdom that when
I act courageously I've got the
stereoscopic optimal grip between the
more nests and misogynist that needs to
be realized in this situation and it's
not just subjective and it's not just an
objective but ayat I have coupled to the
situation in the most appropriate
fashion for that situation and in that
way it's beautiful because I've been
trying to understand in the symposium
when Plato says something and everybody
goes yeah I get that but he goes you
know you move from physical beauty and
then you move to the beauty of
institutions and virtues and everybody
goes goes yeah yeah what the hell are
you talking about like how is it virtue
beautiful like what does and that's my
proposal to you but I think that virtue
but unless a virtuous beauty I'm saying
virtue is the beauty of wisdom it's
right that's what I'm proposing to well
yeah I think there's a I mean if we
define wisdom in a very general sense I
would call it a toroidal sense because
it you know it folds young the going-out
folds back into the coming in yeah so
you've got that and now the very
simplistic geometric structure of a
pyramid right so you if you had beauty
and justice and truth and goodness they
have a convergence point of some kind at
this pain eeeh Slee up going and in
going wisdom function that overflows
maybe back onto them so that that's a
that's the transcendental notion of
know-how yes anything that works is know
how and if know-how is understood to be
what wisdom is that makes a lot of sense
so that anything that functions any
virtue is a form of know-how but virtue
isn't just when we look at a system and
it functions well
so it's expressing the virtue it's
there's also the interior recognition of
that quality so it has a beauty to it
yes attractiveness of some kind
exactly.you yeah that was well said
that's exactly yeah I'm trying to
yeah I'm finding exactly I'm trying to
get that there seems to be this because
part of what I see Plato doing is he's
trying to but extend Beauty he's not
actually explained instead Beauty into
ah and this seems to hacks so he's
trying to extend wonder into ah and this
seems to like correspond to that some
relationship between beauty and wisdom
and that's what I'm trying to get out
here that we pick up on right the beauty
of wisdom and it draws us in and then
eventually we can be you can come into
reverence work and that's what I think
it is to be 5eo Sophia to fall in love
with wisdom it has to me in some deeply
motivational and cognitive sound
attractive to us the other thing about
that for me is that it's so general that
it's potentially could be unpacked or
deployed into all kinds of different
affairs right if you know it as personal
cognition of beauty or is personal
cognition of truth and you might think
well how could I get that same thing in
politics how could I get that same thing
in my exercise routine the more refined
I make the notion the more I'm liable to
be able to find that experience within
any set of functions that works that
expresses the wisdom of know how I think
that's good I mean I would also put in
perspective title and the participatory
no in addition but I think
using no matter their comprehensive
place so that's fine and I think that
goes towards like again that again a
kind of stereoscopic grasping or rocking
of the deep learning that you you
generate the very a you generate
projective you let me use your language
into the variations and then you you
recollect it in into but what's what
like as you get better at burying it you
get better at expecting more deeper
invariants what is much more general
which then allows you to vary it more
and then you get that cycle of deep
learning which i think is part of what
we're talking about as well here yeah
and that is you know i immediately
thought of general relativity when you
said that einstein wanted to call
invariants theory but we are relatively
theory right and we have this sense of
the vast number of changing frames of
reference that have to be taken into
account in some kind of expanded
geometrical hyperspace so it seems very
complex but it's also very simplifying
because he's looking for the non varying
qualities across all frames of reference
that increase the the evolution beyond
Newtonian mechanics involved the
simultaneous refining and simplifying
and vast expanse that's great that's
wonderful that's very good I like that I
didn't know that he was actually wanted
to follow that's really amazing we all
like the argument is we knew about the
relativity thing already Galileo had
described the relativity of measurements
and frames of references the problem was
how do you overcome the relativity by
finding what is invariant I have the
speed of light presented itself as a
good option that's fantastic Thank You
Linda thank you for that thanks first of
all just a good fact to know both for
physics and for cognitive science that
interesting the night sky as an example
are kind of dialectical thinking but but
also just as a pertinent metaphor for
what we're
talking about here and now I like the
way you keep reminding me because it is
it is about Kuna even a bias and like
because although I've been working
really hard with the help of others
between addressing I often don't think I
do think about descriptive cognition
more and more but I I don't give enough
to sort of what you might call the
socio-political aspect of this just
because I'm so critical of their
ideological tyranny and the way it's
sort of the way it terrorizes discourse
so much but what every time you've
invoked it I found it to be well and you
scum I found it to be a justification
yeah it's an interesting field and I you
know people who are working on the arts
the sciences the self development
practices anything where it's very much
about human interiors or interpersonal
relationships can often have a gap when
it comes to politics the end and
legitimately so because it seems so
flawed and trapped in its own category
sets yeah and the people you hear talk
about it are very often either
dismissive or zealots yeah yeah but when
you start to think through like if
you're working on a project and you
think how do we develop people how do we
make a civilization of higher practices
well you know what kinds of operative
social and economic systems would allow
for that and which ones start to
interfere with that right so there's
there's a way of unpacking science and
Dharma into politics I think in a fairly
simple way that we often don't do just
because it seems like such a murky
territory yeah yeah I think that was
very well said
at some point we're running at a pun
today so don't want to jump on that but
I'd like to have a conversation with you
about exactly that topic because it is
but I mean I think I have well you would
know that you have legitimate criticism
or how we've descended if you
this aerial zero-sum game and that there
are we're into the tyranny of the
propositional and all kinds of things
that I think should politically be
criticized and how they contribute to an
exacerbate the meeting crisis but I want
to acknowledge that there's an area that
I well that I'm not seeing through these
are right and I'd invite you to to talk
more about that if you like because I
think that'd be very interesting III I
have a good faith in you that you would
be able to follow through on the framing
you just posed which is to try and get
this into a more helpful framing rather
than in what to be fair what its
prevalently sort of ossified into in a
lot of ways well I would like that very
much I would enjoy that very much
yeah I think that would be an
interesting topic for us to go at and
for me I come from the angle of my own
understanding of what I mean by religion
yes it's the sort of social and
interpersonal analog of this process of
the production of an excess coherence
within the individual subsystems that is
immediately a political affair right
it's a part of and that's what you just
said was beautiful
we're going to this conversation be
careful here because we're coming close
because that's exactly one of my
criticisms that politics is I'll use
neighbors distinction of manifest and
it's manifesting secular but it's latent
ly deeply religious and then it often
comes off as something verging on a
pseudo religion precisely because it
won't acknowledge the religion with the
religiosity what is doing because I
think of a mistake that that will
somehow violate you know the separation
of church and state which is a policy
decision which is a very different from
drawing theoretical connections so like
yes I want more on that right I used
exactly that part of it because that's
part of my my team I don't like the way
and I'm sorry I'm stating that by almost
I'm not just making criticism there's
something about me that is put off by
the way politics tries to take the place
of religion and that we've had
disastrous consequences because of that
on in the 20th century and so I want to
know what it's like to unpack politics
the way you're suggesting that like that
accounts for its religiosity without
falling into the Titanic evils of the
pseudo religious ideologies that have
drenched the world in flight that's what
that's for me that a really difficult
problem of a get expanding this to the
political domain sure well I'm gonna
make sure not to say anything about that
so that we can go in fresh yeah it's
time to work on that I'm gonna bring us
back around in a weird way by touching
on your brief meta comment about how
this is going yeah because I had two
flashes well you said the first was that
this process of bringing things together
which is ideally trans rational rather
than pre rational yes that that's the
that's the way you have to go at it if
what you want to hear is the leading
edge of someone's insight into
structures yes
that kind of falls out of them during
that process whereas a propositional
debate is based on previously solidified
assertions that you're gonna build up
right so that's a very important process
in our social evolution however it gets
in the way of the immediacy of staying
at our shared leading edge yeah unlike
that and the other part of it is I had
that that's how I see me chase idea of
the will to power right he's trying to
speak to a subjective analog of a basic
process of energetics but that process
is the cloud and the lightning it's a
coming together of a bunch of charges
into a combined discharge is the
level more and more intensely that's
where how he sees the empowerment event
occurring I think that's good
Nietzsche was famously difficult to
interpret because my reading of him is
extremely idiosyncratic so I think
that's right technology for 40
Villalobos where are you getting that
coupled Co emergence coupled Co
emergence so where I'm not trying to
show that I'm right I'm trying to get
into right relationship with you and
reality and it has gone well that you
and I get to a place collectively that
we couldn't get to individually it's the
overflow that you talk about I think
that for me if that's that's me that's
the defining feature of this now the
Nietzschean core puts me in mind of he
gave one clear example of the evil bitch
it is writing it's good time which is
not what most people think and what's
really interesting I just I was just
sitting in on somebody who's defending a
thesis on good and Barfield and Steiner
and the whole new way of seeing the
whole way of newly doing science which
is all about participatory conformity
and coupling to the phenomena rather
than just objectively representing and
predicting about it and so it's about
it's about science practice biologically
right rather than just predictably and
so I was thinking about what if Goethe
is teaching being honest and it's always
hard to tell him he's playing or he's
saying right but if let's say he's
saying rather than just playing good to
is the example of the new revenge then I
think your interpretation that you just
made there it's actually a very good one
because I mean that's exactly the kind
of relationship I think good and good to
what I was hoping that you know in this
on knowing flow you get then you realize
the earth form of the foot on
like almost in the Platonic sense I get
to go through this neat transformative
deep learning all this stuff we've been
talking about and then the phenomena
right actually discloses itself to you
yeah dirty' is a very good example of
what I would call an authentic religious
figure whether they're socially
recognized as being that or not but he's
science and art and poetry and ecology
and botany and like down the line he
embodies an integration of the genres of
social activity in a way that seems to
manifest itself as some transcendental
quality about his historical person as
well so that's very very well said ok
well I think that's a good place to
perhaps try to bring it to a close we
know right here next time for politics
yeah that would be really thank you for
this discussion well this is via logos
for me and I always find these like you
said they co-create something emergent
that I find very very helpful so thank
you very much
and I look forward to you to our next
time together when we could get into
hopefully the wisdom within the
political debate yeah always a pleasure
John I look forward to the next one
thank you very much